Inventory of the Gregory Family Papers 1829-1920
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Gregory Family Papers 1829-19201880-1900
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2008.138
0.30
The Gregory Family Papers follow the family of patriarch Virginia Governor John Munford Gregory and wife Amanda Wallace through three generations with letters dating from the 1820’s to the 1920’s. Most items are letters between family members and grant insight into the daily activities and concerns of the Gregory family. The collection also includes correspondence between members of the Gregory family and other acquaintances, including members of the John Tyler family. While most letters are of a personal nature, some also touch on the issues of politics, education, religion, and agriculture. The collection is rich in genealogical information on the Gregory family and related Croshaw, Graves, West, and White families, as well as history of the family’s war involvement. In addition to letters, the collection includes newspaper articles, family documents, and two diaries kept by John M. Gregory’s daughter, Mattie Galbraith, in the late 1870’s. There are also seven cased images of members of the Gregory Family, including Amanda Wallace Gregory, Amanda's sister (Elizabeth Christie Powell), William Wallace Gregory, and Mary "Mollie" Gregory.
Galbraith, Martha, 1851 - 1924; Gregory, Evelyn "Eva", circa 1840; Gregory, John M. II, 1804-1884; Gregory, John M. III, circa 1840; Gregory, Martha "Amanda", 1809 - 1894 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center from Letitia Gregory Galbraith Machado on 12/16/2008.
Biographical Note
Martha "Mattie" Gregory was born in Charles City County in 1851 to Judge John Munford Gregory and Amanda Wallace Gregory. In 1879, she married Robert Davidson Galbraith and relocated to Spartanburg, SC. She and her husband had five children, though only two (Letitia "Letty" Gregory Galbraith and John Munford Gregory "Greg" Galbraith) survived to adulthood. Mattie Galbraith died in 1924.
Scope and Contents
The Gregory Family Papers follow the family of patriarch Virginia Governor John Munford Gregory and wife Amanda Wallace through three generations with letters dating from the 1820’s to the 1920’s. Most items are letters between family members and grant insight into the daily activities and concerns of the Gregory family. The collection also includes correspondence between members of the Gregory family and other acquaintances, including members of the John Tyler family. While most letters are of a personal nature, some also touch on the issues of politics, education, religion, and agriculture. The collection is rich in genealogical information on the Gregory family and related Croshaw, Graves, West, and White families, as well as history of the family’s war involvement. In addition to letters, the collection includes newspaper articles, family documents, and two diaries kept by John M. Gregory’s daughter, Mattie Galbraith, in the late 1870’s. There are also seven cased images of members of the Gregory Family, including Amanda Wallace Gregory, Amanda's sister (Elizabeth Christie Powell), William Wallace Gregory, and Mary "Mollie" Gregory.
Arrangement of Materials
In order by recipient, when applicable, otherwise in order by subject matter. Then, within folder, in chronological order.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Family Name:
Galbraith Family; Gregory Family
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Diaries; Legal documents; Newspapers
Geographic Name:
Virginia--Genealogy; Virginia--History--19th century.
Occupation:
Virginia. Governor (1842-1843: Gregory)
Topical Term:
Charles City County (Va.)--History--19th century.; College of William and Mary--History--19th century.; College of William and Mary--Students.; James City County (Va.)--History--19th century.; Suisun (Calif.)--History; United States--Politics and government--1865-1900.; Women--Virginia--Social life and customs
Detailed Description of the Collection
  Series 1: Correspondence
- Correspondence, 1829-1920
  Correspondence between members of the Gregory family, organized by recipient.
  - Letters to Letty Galbraith, 1893-1920 (1)
    Item by item description:
    Letter from Letty Gregory to niece Letty Galbraith
    22 February 1893
    Family
    Health, Sleep, Diet
    Included: Note from Amanda Wallace Gregory
    Letter from John M. Gregory to Letty “Missy” Galbraith
    28 February 1894
    Death of Amanda Wallace Gregory
    California, Missy to Visit
    Letter from John Gregory to Letty “Missy” Galbraith
    16 March 1894
    Her Illness, Benefits of California Climate
    His Children
    Postcard from Elisabeth W. B. to Letty Galbraith
    14 September 1920’s
    Gloucester County Court House
    John M. Gregory Tablet
  - Letters to Mattie Galbraith, 1884-1918 (2)
    Note by Mattie Galbraith
    7 October 1884
    Death of Mattie Galbraith’s Child, Amanda
    Cause of Death Letter from Amanda Wallace Gregory to daughter Mattie Galbraith
    20 July 1885
    Gifts, Visitors
    Illness
    Religion
    Letter from Amanda Wallace Gregory to daughter Mattie Galbraith
    29 September 1885
    Family, Illness
    Friends, Company
    Bishop, Robert D. Galbraith’s Confirmation
    5 July 1888
    Family Illness, Amanda Gregory’s Eye Trouble
    Mattie’s Children
    Note from Amanda Wallace Gregory to daughter Mattie Galbraith
    Eye Trouble
    Letter from John M. Gregory to sister, Mattie Galbraith
    J.M. Gregory’s Civil War Service
    Captain Wallace, General Stonewall Jackson
    Letter from T.B. to cousin, Mattie Galbraith
    Family, Health
    Genealogy
    Letter from T. B. to cousin Mattie Galbraith
    Children
    Family Genealogy
    Letter from M. Gregory to sister, Mattie Galbraith
    4 March
    Family News
    Amanda Gregory’s Grandchildren
    Recent, Controversial Marriage
    Added Note by Grandchild
    Friends and Family
    Dressmaking
    Racist Remark
    Letter from Mille A. A. to Mattie Galbraith
    17 June
    Family, Friends, Weather, Household Concerns
    Cherry Harvest
    Postcard from Amanda Wallace Gregory to daughter Mattie Galbraith
    13 April 1889
    Family, Photography, Books
    Rob Galbraith, Health
    8 August 1890
    Public Schooling, Travel, Health, Clothing
    Letter from Greg M. W. (?) to Mattie Galbraith
    15 July
    Family, Friends, Travel Plans
    Death of “Dear Ones”
    Letter from Margaret (?) to sister Mattie Galbraith
    9 November 1890
    Family and Friend News, Family Illness
    Death, Sympathy
    Baptism
    Letter from M.E. to sister-in-law Mattie Galbraith
    17 June 1891
    Health, Weather
    Recent Photograph
    Price of Potatoes and Refrigerators
    Gossip, Recent Scandal
    Letter from M. E. to sister-in-law Mattie Galbraith
    23 January 1892
    Family News, Recent Visit from Robert Galbraith
    27 April 1892
    Family, Family Activities, Health
    Bishop Visit
    Letter from Letty (?) to sister Mattie Galbraith
    15 February 1893
    Company, Visit from Mr. Tyler
    Health, Doctor, Benefits of “Hyperphosphites”
    Valentines
    Alcohol
    7 June 1893
    Family, Dressmaking
    Travels, Williamsburg
    Recent Marriage
    Fruits and Flowers of the Season
    Letter from Ms. Gregory to sister Mattie Galbraith
    Death of a Betty C.
    Planned Visit
    Health of Rob Galbraith
    Scrapbooks
    Amanda Wallace Gregory
    Death of a Mother of Six
    Letter from Margaret (?) to her sister Mattie Galbraith
    21 April 1890’s (?)
    Serious Illness of Mattie’s Son, Rob
    Company, Social Engagements
    3 June 1894
    Letter from Eva Gregory to sister-in-law, Mattie Galbraith
    30 October 1894
    Mattie’s Eye Troubles
    4 July 1895
    Mattie’s Recent Move
    Importance of Education, Sons and Stanford University
    Fourth of July Festivities
    Christmas Time 1895
    Thanks for Christmas Presents [the ring], the Children
    House Fire, Holiday Chaos
    17 January 1896
    Thanks for Christmas Gifts
    Detailing of House Fire
    Description of her Children
    Stanford University, Honor Code
    Seeks Advice on Hiring Chinese vs. Japanese Servant
    Letter from T.T.C. Gregory to aunt Mattie Galbraith
    6 June 1896
    Tom’s Professor to Visit Mattie’s Town
    John Gregory’s Graduation from Stanford, Tom and John Career Plans
    Letter from Thomas Gregory to Aunt, Mattie Galbraith
    14 August 1896
    Stanford University
    Friends: D. Smith, Charley Doyle
    Yachting Trip
    Letter from Laura R.G. May to Mattie Galbraith
    11 November 1896
    Death of Mattie Galbraith’s Child, Sympathy
    Letter from Truxton Gregory to aunt, Mattie Galbraith
    28 November 1896
    His Christmas Present [ring]
    His Baseball Team
    “Ladies Stome Journal”
    Letter from A. Nilsen (?) to cousin Mattie Galbraith
    30 December 1896
    Receipt of Present for Hattie, Travel Plans with Hattie
    Health, Past Christmas
    Letter from S.G. Tyler to Mattie Galbraith
    7 January 1897
    Childhood reminiscence
    January 1897
    Thanks for Gifts
    Fears of House Burning
    In Depth on Children, Husband
    Included: Note from Eva’s son, Alfred, to cousin Gregory
    Letter from John M. Gregory to sister Mattie Galbraith
    February 1897
    History of the Family’s Military Record, Civil War, War of 1812, Revolutionary War
    Letter from Gertrude Gregory to Mattie Galbraith
    1 March 1897
    Gertrude’s Brother’s Visit and Illness
    Death in Gregory Family
    Earthquake
    Letter from Eva Gregory to Sister-in-Law, Mattie Galbraith
    Opinions on Women’s Rights, Upcoming Vote
    Stanford University, Sons’ Studies
    Health, “Sad State of the Garden”
    Letter from J. E. B. to Mattie Galbraith
    30 December 1898
    Death of Mutual Friend, Gratitude for Token of the Deceased
    7 June 1899
    Death of Eva’s Son, John M. Gregory, Jr.
    Included: Obituary of John M. Gregory, Jr.
    3 June 1899
    “Fatal Plunge”, Account of Deadly Accident
    Summer 1899
    Death and Funeral of Eva’s Son, John M. Gregory
    Family Grief, Community Response
    Letter from William T. Clapers (?) to Mattie Galbraith
    Apologies
    Unable to Provide Requested Information (Possibly Sermon Related)
    Letter from Letty to her cousin Mattie Galbraith
    1906(?)
    Gregory Genealogy, Gregory Records in Richmond
    Colonial Dames, Daughters of the Revolution, Daughters of the Confederacy
    Transcribed Mrs. Lyon G. Tyler Letter
    25 April 1906
    His Mother’s Pneumonia
    Recent Earthquake
    Letter from Gertrude Gregory to husband’s aunt Mattie Galbraith
    6 October 1906
    Illness of Gertrude’s Brother and Baby
    Burning of House and Move to Family House
    Political Campaign in Suisun, CA
    Husband(T.T.C. Gregory)’s Reelection, Important Trial
    Homesickness, Isolation
    Railroad
    Jefferson Davis Chapter
    Her Sons, New Granddaughter [Gertrude & Tom’s]
    Letter from Minnie (?) to cousins Robert and Mattie Galbraith
    8 July 1918
    Family, Travel Plans
  - Letters to Robert Davidson Galbraith, 1879-1892 (3)
    Letter by Robert Davidson Galbraith
    7 July 1879
    Recent marriage to Mattie Gregory
    Ceremony, Reception, Honeymoon Plans
    Letter from a Doctor to Robert Galbraith (?)
    26 October 1883
    Eye Problems, Medical Advice
    Letter from Carrie Prag to Robert D. Galbraith
    20 November 1883
    Loan Request, Home Repairs
    Family and Friend News, Recent Marriages
    Letter from Margaret (?) to brother-in-law Robert Galbraith
    1 March 1892
    Gratitude
  - Letters to Amanda Wallace Gregory, 1829-1894 (4)
    Letter from E.M. Davison to Miss Amanda Wallace
    12 July 1829
    Shared Family
    Letter to Amanda Wallace
    5 July 1832
    Religious Testimony, Religious Conventions
    Death, Salvation
    Letter from M. Gregory to mother Amanda Wallace Gregory
    12 February 1881
    Amanda Gregory’s Birthday
    Cold Winter Weather, Winter Weather Colds
    Family, John Gregory’s Sons
    Letter from John M. Gregory to mother Amanda Wallace Gregory
    12 February 1883
    Amanda Gregory’s 74th Birthday
    John Gregory’s Sons, Illness and Education
    Weather, Family
    Letter from William Gregory to mother Amanda Wallace Gregory
    8 February 1884
    Amanda Gregory’s 75th Birthday
    William’s Wife, Health, Servant Search
    William’s Professional Duties as Doctor
    Weather, Roads
    Letter from John M. Gregory and Thomas Gregory to mother/grandmother Amanda Wallace Gregory
    September 1885
    Thomas’s Schooling
    Dinner Menu
    Letter from Sam Stevens to cousin Amanda Wallace Gregory
    25 December 1886
    Death of Amanda Gregory’s sister, Betsy, Sympathy, Religion
    Letter from John M. Gregory to mother, Amanda Wallace Gregory
    30 May 1888
    Birth of 3rd Son
    Condition of Wife, Comments on Older Two Boys
    12 June 1888
    Health, Family
    Crops
    21 April 1889
    Family Health
    Children, Summer Vacation
    Weather
    20 January 1890
    His Recent Visit to Virginia
    Letter from Julia Armistead to Amanda Wallace Gregory
    11 February 1891
    Family, Health, Weather
    Letter from John P. Tyler to Amanda Wallace Gregory
    20 July 1892
    Death of her Child, Sympathy
    Letter from Rob Galbraith to grandmother Amanda Wallace Gregory
    11 February 1893
    Note by Amanda Wallace Gregory
    15 September 1893
    Bequeaths Belongings to Relatives
    25 January 1894
    Amanda Gregory’s Malaria, Recovery
    His Longing for Home/Virginia
  - Letters to John M. Gregory, 1843-1883 (5)
    Letter from Thomas Wallace to John M. Gregory
    20 June 1843
    Instructions to Purchase and Emancipate Slave Boy
    Letter from John M. Gregory to his father John M. Gregory
    8 July 1872
    First Communication in Years
    Son’s New Wife, Their Frugal Lifestyle
    New Town, Elections
    Family, Future Visit
    24 June 1873
    Father’s Birthday, Father-Son Relationship
    Son’s Career Plans, Application for County Office
    County Politics
    Family, Lifestyle, Health
    Letter from John M. Gregory Jr., to father, John M. Gregory Sr.
    26 September 1880
    Politics, Presidential Election
    Crops, Drought
    8 July 1880
    Father’s Birthday
    Legal Work
    Politics, “Greenback Movement”
    Letter from John M. Gregory to father John M. Gregory
    8 July 1883
    Father’s 79th Birthday
    Son’s Judgeship, Plans
    Family, Weather
  - Letters to Letty Gregory, 1873-1902 (6)
    Letter from E.J.S. to Letty Gregory
    11 February 1873
    Death of William (Probably her Brother)
    Legal Proceedings Following Death
    Letter to Letty Gregory
    November 1874 (?)
    Expression of Emotions
    New Baby and Mother
    Letter from John Munford Gregory to daughter Letty Gregory
    3 November
    Photo of Child Who Died
    Cooper Line, Ancestry, War History
    Conversation with grandson Rob Galbraith
    Political Opinions
    Letter from Amanda Wallace Gregory to daughter Letty Gregory
    Family and Friends
    Martha’s Wedding Clothes
    Letter from Lyon G. Tyler to Letty Gregory
    17 November 1892
    Gregory Genealogy
    Power Family Research
    Health
    Letter from A. Van De Vyuer to Letty Gregory
    8 August 1893
    Health, Travel Plans
    Death of Mollie Gregory
    Letter from David Gardiner Tyler to Letty Gregory
    27 August 1893-7
    Congress, Washington D.C.
    17 February 1894
    Death of Letty’s mother Amanda Wallace Gregory
    Testimonial of her Character
    22 February 1897
    Letty’s Travel Plans
    Recent Parties
    Desire to See Letty
    6 December 1902
    His Political Trials and Successes
    United States Congress
  - Letters to Other (or Unidentified) Gregory Family Members, 1869-1909 (7)
    Letter from John M. Gregory to wife Eva Gregory
    25 July 1869
    His Business Trip, Sudden Illness
    Travel Plans
    Friends and Family, Weather
    Housework Instructions
    Letter from Virginia Trayler
    Julia Armistead, Tea Party Plans
    Letter from M. to niece Mollie Gregory
    Family, Travel, Weather
    1 February 1890
    Weather, Family, the Children, Health
    Residence in Mexico, Mexican Food
    Letty Gregory
    Letter from Amanda Wallace Gregory to grandson Rob Galbraith
    29 December 1891
    Letter from Amanda Wallace Gregory to a cousin
    18 January 1892
    Old Church in Petersburg, Large Fire of 1816
    Letter from Amanda Wallace Gregory to a Grandchild
    1 May 1893
    Recent Marriage of this Grandchild, Marital Advice
    Letter from Amanda Wallace Gregory to Rob Galbraith
    16 August 1893
    Health, Amanda Gregory’s Failing Eyesight
    On Envelope: Rob Dies of Spiral Meningitis
    Letter by William B. Hamilton
    Early 1900’s
    Commentary on a Mr. Petty
    Letter from E .F. J. (?)
    19 February 1909
    Religion, Criticisms of Church
  - Lettters to Thomas and William Wallace, 1832-1833 (8)
    Letter from Thomas Wallace to his Uncle
    7 February 1832
    College of William and Mary, Studies, Prank, Potential Duel
    Series of Balls, Parties – “scene of dissipation”
    Letter from William Wallace to his Brother
    2 November 1833
    Letter-writing
    Lecture of Dr. Magill
    Studies, Languages, Expenses
    Home Comforts, Music, Food
    M.N. Washington and Monticello Break-in
  Series 2: Genealogical Notes
- Genealogical Notes
  Notes on the Genealogy of the Gregory Family, made by members of the family, and letters written about Gregory and related family genealogy, including the Croshaw, West, Graves, White, Wallace, and Cooper families. Item by item descriptions follow:
  Notes by Letty Gregory
  9 October 1897
  Family Genealogy, War History
  Notes
  Gregory Family Genealogy from 17th-18th Century
  Genealogy of Croshaw, West, Graves, and White Families 1655-1804
  Letter from Mattie Gregory to Lyon G. Tyler
  25 September 1896
  Gregory Genealogical Information, as Requested
  Sent Elsewhere for Revision
  Letter to Gregory Family from Distant Relative
  Author’s Connection to Gregory Family (Shared Great-Grandmother)
  Note to Mattie Galbraith
  Wallace and Cooper Family Genealogy
  Letter from Lorabel Wallace Brooks to Professor David Duncan Wallace
  Culbertson, Wallace Genealogy
  Note
  Genealogy Scraps, Wallace, Cooper
  Genealogy, Wallace and Cooper Families
  - (9)
  Series 3: Gregory Family Documents
- Gregory Family Documents, 1847-1907
  Document regarding dedication of Croshaw, Graves, Gregory family
  pews and pew doors at Bruton Parish Church.
  Indenture, by John Martin and John M. Gregory
  15 September 1847
  Legal Document, Land, Servitude
  Business Letter from the Virginia Trust Company to Mattie Galbraith
  30 September 1895
  Legacy of Letty Gregory
  24 September 1907
  Illness, Family
  Includes land warrants and grants dated from 1792 – 1907
  Gregory Family Right to Land due to Revolutionary War
  Service of William and John Gregory
  - (10)
  Series 4: Gregory Family Deaths
- Gregory Family Deaths, 1884-1903
  Letters, certificates, newspaper articles, telegrams, and court resolves relating to the deaths of members of the Gregory family. Item by item description:
  Telegram from Letty Gregory to Galbraiths
  10 April 1884
  Death of father, John M. Gregory
  Resolution by James City County Circuit Court, Hon. R.L. Henley, Hon. J.M. Jeffries, Gov. Robert H. Armistead, etc.)
  2 June 1884
  John Munford Gregory, Character and Accomplishments
  Condolences to Family
  Resolution by Citizens of Charles City Country
  20 May 1884
  John Munford Gregory, Career and Integrity
  Two Newspaper Obituaries Attached
  Certificate of William T. Gregory
  25 March 1889
  “Apostolic Rite of Laying on of Hands”
  Signed by Rector John P. Tyler
  Card
  10 May 1889
  “In Loving Remembrance of William T. Gregory”
  Two Poems about Death
  Issue of the Richmond Dispatch
  14 October 1884
  Obituary of Georgia Wilson Galbraith, Young Daughter of Mattie Gregory and R.D. Galbraith
  Letter from John Lamb (of U.S. House of Representatives) to Mattie Galbraith
  1903
  David Gardiner Tyler, Judge Wright
  Presentation of Tablets Honoring John Munford Gregory I
  Letter from David Gardiner Tyler to Mattie Galbraith
  29 September 1903
  Honor of Presenting
  Request for Data, John M. Gregory’s Career
  - (11)
  Series 5: Newspaper Articles
- Newspaper Articles, 1903-1904
  Newspaper issues and clippings containing articles related to the Gregory family, including family genealogy and a wedding. Item by item description:
  Page from the Southside Sentinel (Duplicates)
  18 December 1903
  Article: Gloucester Court House Unveiling Ceremony
  Tablet in Honor of John M. Gregory
  Address by Hon. D. Gardiner Tyler
  History of Gregory and Family
  Issue of the Solano Republican
  24 April 1903
  Article: Fashionable Wedding of T.T.C. (Thomas) Gregory to Gertrude Martin
  Article from the Times Dispatch
  20 November 1904
  Genealogy of Gregory Family (traces, with gaps, to mid 1600’s)
  Gregory Coat of Arms, Historical Information
  4 December 1904
  Supplement to Previous Article
  - (12)
  Series 6: Diaries of Mattie Gregory Galbraith
- Diaries of Mattie Gregory Galbraith, 1876-1881
  Two personal diaries kept by Mattie Gregory leading up to and immediately after her marriage to Robert Davidson Galbraith, detailing "the many joys and few trials" of her life.
  - Mattie Gregory Galbraith Diary, 1876-1878 (13)
    Diary kept by Mattie Gregory in one of her father's old journals. The diary is full of Mattie's day-to-day activities, stories of her family, impressions of friends and acquaintances, and tales of the sorrows, the quarrels, the joys, and love in her life and the lives of those around her.
  - Mattie Gregory Galbraith Diary, 1878-1881 (14)
    In this diary, Mattie Gregory continues to record the daily events of her life in Charles City County, Virginia. Near the end, she deals with the stress and excitment of her engagement and the joy of marriage and motherhood.
  Series 7: Photographs
- Photographs
  - Gregory Family Photographs, 1856-1870 (15)
    Removed to artifact collection.
    Framed photographs of Gregory Family members:
    Mary "Mattie" Martha Gregory's sister
    William Wallace Gregory
    James P. and Mary E. Purcell
    AWG's sister
    three unidentified women.